In the last video, we
briefly discussed typical modeling patterns
in Petri nets, some of which
we had already seen in examples,
but which we
explicitly addressed again there.
One of them was
the mutual exclusion or synchronization.
We also discussed this with
the example of the feeding philosophers.
How you can avoid the problems with
two philosophers that you have with three philosophers.
Another requirement that one often has in
practical modeling with Petri nets is that
one wants to say
something about the capacity of
individual places or, in
particular, to bound the capacity.
What is
meant by this?
For example, you want to make sure that no
matter how the Petri net fires, there can never
be more than a certain number of tokens on
each of the individual places, and you also want to
be able to specify different such
upper capacity bounds for different places.
This is not exactly the same
as the boundedness of Petri nets.
Because that was a property that a
Petri net may or may not have.
You have a Petri net and you make a
statement about all the markings that can be reached.
That, for example, a certain maximum number
of tokens per place is never exceeded.
That would be
something that comes up.
One has a Petri net
and it results for this Petri
net that never more tokens
can accumulate on a place.
That is something
different than saying:
You want to
express in modeling
that, for example, a particular spot
never picks up more than five tokens.
Even if it could happen
during normal firing of the Petri
net that six tokens accumulate on the spot there,
one would like to express in the model that
then no firing at all
may take place in that case.
While the question
of boundedness/unboundedness assumes:
One fires according to the definition
of Petri nets and then observes whether
many tokens can accumulate
on a spot or not.
Suppose instead we want to
constrain that in the model.
So for example, if we describe
a snack vending machine, that might
be we want to express that
there would never be more than
20 items of a
given snack type in stock.
Or if we think back to the
afternoon modeling (which I had gone through
as an example), there was this Playstation place
where a reservoir of tokens could accumulate, how
many times after that the
action "play" could then be performed.
And you might have
wanted to somehow express that
there are never more than seven tokens
on that spot at any one time.
That if this is the case,
it is not allowed to continue.
This is the kind of restriction one
might want to impose on one's Petri nets.
How might one
go about doing that?
One has to consider:
How can I model this?
And one way out
would be to simply say:
One makes
that explicit.
You sort of introduce a
new kind of Petri net.
We'll do that
for a moment.
That doesn't
have to scare
you because it's a very simple
definition, also has very clear semantics.
You could say you just extend
the notion of Petri nets and introduce
so-called "Petri
nets with capacities".
How could
one do that?
One would have to
express this extra information.
One would want to take a normal
Petri net and add capacities to that.
By which is meant that
if S is the set of
places, you simply specify another
natural number for each place.
One can do this
in a capacity function,
a mapping from the place
set into the natural numbers.
This is to express that never
(not in the initial marking, but
also never later) there can be more tokens
on a place than k specifies for this place.
Thus in particular for the initial marking m0 it
must be true that less than or equal to k.
Less-equal in
which sense?
In the sense in which
we can compare such functions.
This is a marking in the same sense
as the initial marking is a marking, and
as the pre- and post-weighting functions
in the Petri net were markings.
And for such functions,
which we called markings,
we had
introduced a comparison.
And as a reminder, very
importantly, that was the place-by-place comparison.
That was
not simply:
How many total tokens are in m0
and how many total tokens are in
the capacity function when you
evaluate it for all the places?
But it was
about the place-by-place comparison.
So for each place it must hold that m0
of d is less than-equal to k of s.
Which means exactly
that the initial marking
on no place carries more
tokens than the capacity function allows.
And we would include this
capacity function as a modeler.
Of course, it's not particularly interesting here
if k returns zero for a place.
So we would expect there
to always be positive numbers here.
Formally, one could also allow k
to be zero for a given s.
But this would
mean that you never
want to have any
tokens on this place.
Then one does not need
to introduce this place at all.
So it would
not make sense.
Interestingly, the pipe tool that we've been
working with (that I've been working with,
and maybe you have too, in
practice) knows about such Petri nets.
It knows the notion
of "Petri nets with capacities".
I had not used that there, but
there you can write capacities at the places.
And then this fulfills exactly the
intuition, which I had already mentioned.
So each place s may
contain at most k(s) tokens, ever.
This is
very important:
So this must hold not
only for the initial marking,
but also when the
Petri net evolves and fires,
it will be ensured that there are never
more than k(s) tokens on the place s.
If there were, then a firing
operation would simply not be performed.
How do we represent
this in the graphical representation?
This is just
the mathematical indication.
There we will simply write
these capacities next to the places.
So far, we have written numbers
in the Petri net only at the
connections, at the arrows from places to transitions
and from transitions to places, with which we
have expressed the weight there,
from the precondition and postcondition function.
Now we will also allow numbers
to be attached to the places.
Namely exactly the numbers which
should correspond to the capacity.
How could this look
like, such an example network?
For example like this: a normal
Petri net, as you have seen it
many times before; but now there is
the annotation 2 at the position s1.
So at place s1, 2 would be annotated, at
place s2, 1 would be annotated, and that would
correspond (in terms of the previous slide) to this
function mapping s1 to 2 and s2 to 1.
Very
importantly:
These annotations are now at these
places and not at the arrows.
There should still
be such numbers there.
They have then the
same meaning as before, namely
describe the before and after weight
of transitions with respect to single places.
And in addition there can be just these numbers
at the places, or for a Petri net with
capacities there must be even at each
place such a number written on it.
What is
the idea here?
Why do we do
this in the example?
We would want to achieve with
it that on this place never more
than two tokens lie and on
this place never more than one token.
That is,
certain firing
operations that would be possible if you
ignore the capacities should not be allowed now.
If we look at this Petri
net and forget the two annotations
here, we could
easily consider that
all three transitions are
enabled in this initial station.
Because t1 can fire because
there is a token here.
And t2 can fire because there is a token here.
Also t3 can fire because there is a token here.
However, if we
take the capacities into
account, we would
have to conclude:
No, t1 cannot
fire after all.
Up to now it was important for the
firing of t1 that all preconditions are fulfilled,
i.e. that there is a token
here (because there is this input arrow).
Now with these capacities it
would have to be checked additionally
that the transition has also the
opportunity to deposit its output tokens.
And here this would
mean: consume a token from
here, which is also present, all good,
but also deposit a token in s2.
And that would not be allowed in
the constellation shown here, because there is
already a token here and it says
here that there may only be one token.
This means that the firing of t1, which is
actually possible in this situation, would suddenly not be allowed.
On the other hand, t3
would be allowed to fire.
It would consume this token and
has no problem to deposit anything,
because there are
no exit arrows.
And also t2 is allowed to fire, because
t2 finds a token in the precondition place and
is allowed to put a token
in the only postcondition place of t2.
Because there is already one
token, but there may be two.
So here t2 may
fire, but not t1.
And t3
may also fire.
That would be the
definition, which simply corresponds to
what is required here
for this one firing operation.
Of course, this has
to be expressed formally.
So the semantics would
have to be adapted.
But that is
also done quickly.
Let's remember, previously it
was said that a
transition is activated in a certain
marking m, in this case for m0.
So far it was only required that the
marking corresponding to the preweight function of the
transition is less than or
equal to the current marking.
Because this would mean in the end
that per place the transitions do not request
more tokens than are present in
the current situation, per place-wise comparison.
And here comes now the expression for
the fact that we must look evenly
also at the issuing points, whether there
is so to speak still enough place.
What does
that mean?
We look at what happens
when this condition is met.
Then I could say in principle
with normal firing in a Petri net:
We just subtract from the current marking
the pre-weights for the current transition we want
to fire, and add (again,
in places, with these two operations
we introduced in an earlier video) the
place specifications for this concrete transition, that
is, in each case how many
tokens should be put in the places.
And then we see if what
comes out (what would come out
in normal firing) is still
less-than-equal to the capacity marking.
And only if this is so (that's
why it says "and if it is allowed"),
the tradition t in the
marking m may fire at all.
Before, only this
first condition was required.
Now the second
condition is additionally required.
And if this is also fulfilled,
the transition is allowed to fire.
What
happens then?
Then what is written here
is simply the new marking.
This was also the
case with normal firing.
When firing a normal Petri
net, this had to be fulfilled.
Now it is additionally required that the
new marking that would come out is
less-than-equal to
the capacity function.
And only then the transition is allowed to
fire and of course leads exactly to this marking.
Here it is enforced that
always at all reachable markings
the capacity function is
not exceeded at any place.
This is
written here again.
So there it is ensured
exactly that the transitions fire only
if they would
not break the capacities.
That's exactly what
would happen here.
So if we were to fire t1 here,
then the capacitance would be exceeded at this point.
So this firing
is simply forbidden.
What would that mean
for the reachability graph?
It will be smaller, more
restricted compared to the reachability
graph that would result
if we ignore these capacities.
So here would be the
accessibility graph for this concrete example.
There, ultimately, you
can see exactly:
In the initial marking, t2 and
t3 are fireable, but t1 is not.
So in the initial marking that we see
here, (1,1) is exactly this input node (the initial
node in the reachability graph),
there t1 is not activated.
Although, if we were to ignore these
two annotations here, t1 may well fire.
So t2 can
fire, t3 can fire.
What comes out is exactly the same as
what would come out in a normal Petri net.
Only, when we look at
which further transitions are possible,
we always check
which transitions are
activated, taking into
account these capacity bounds.
Here it has an effect above all
here that we may not fire t1 here.
If, on the other
hand, we have fired
t3, which leads to the marking (1,0),
then this token would have disappeared here.
Then we are also
allowed to fire t1.
That's why the t1 transition is possible here,
because it puts the token from here to
there and that's allowed, because even after
that there's still only one token here.
Not like here, where if
we had also fired t1, there
would have been two tokens on
the second position (which is not allowed).
The other transitions are all
allowed as they are here,
and also result
from the definition.
Here, we would have effectively simply
prevented certain firing events by this
specification, and therefore restricted
the reachability graph to this
behavior (and not had another
transition for example here with t1).
You can do
it that way.
Then one would just have to
handle this new kind of Petri nets.
As I said, the tool
we saw can already do that.
However, we would then have
to start adapting all our terms.
We would now have to transfer our mathematical
terms (the properties we have been looking at)
from the normal, simple Petri nets
to these "Petri nets with capacities".
Maybe we don't
want to do that.
Maybe we would like to continue
working with the simple Petri nets we
have come to
know so far.
And interestingly, one
can do just that.
There is a way to accomplish what
we have done here without doing these
annotations in any Petri net
that works with such capacity bounds.
Instead, create an equivalent Petri
net that gets by with
simple means (so
doesn't need such annotation),
but still achieves the behavior that
is enforced here by the capacities.
So in particular, in the end also for
these rewritten Petri nets here in the example
such a reachability graph should come out and
just about t1 should not be fireable from
this initial state (which would be possible
if we would simply ignore the annotations).
We do not want
to ignore the annotations.
We just want to
deal with them differently.
So the insight here is that
you can also achieve this kind of
capacity bound without immediately introducing
a new Petri net type.
And that is by
applying a modeling pattern.
Namely, you rewrite what you want to have
with the means of a simple Petri net.
It's a bit of
a trick, so to
speak, that you use in modeling,
but here you do it systematically.
What is
the idea?
How do we
go about it?
Well, the basic idea is that
we express, so to speak, this
capacity (the fact that there can be no
more than a certain number of tokens on
each of the places) by introducing
an extra additional place for each place.
A so-called complement place, on which
we create a reservoir, so to speak.
In this reservoir, we always keep a
record of the maximum number of tokens that
may be put on
the original place s.
So in the example just
now we had two places.
For each place we
add a so-called complement place.
Simply a place that
has a new name,
but where we can still tell
which original place it belongs to.
We can do that by
using the same place name and
just putting an overline over
it like that, a bar.
That becomes a
normal Petri net again,
where we don't give
any annotations for the capacities.
So we have to encode that information differently, and
for example, yes, we have to specify an initial
marking for our new complement
places (so we say what the
initial marking for those complement
places contains in terms of values).
And that's where we see
that the capacity function comes in.
Namely, we're just going to put exactly
as many tokens on the complement places as
would be allowed according to the capacity, but
are not actually already present in the initial marking.
So if the capacity would say, on
place s five tokens may lie, in the
initial marking of the Petri net however
on this place s only three tokens lie,
then we would put in the initial marking 5
- 3 = 2 tokens on the complement place.
So m0 of s-bar would
then be k(s) - m0(s).
This ensures that, at least initially, the sum
of the tokens in the place itself and in
its complement place gives
exactly the desired capacity that
we would have written to the
place in the Petri net with capacities.
In this way, we can make sure that
this is the case for the initial marking.
And in what follows, we'll
make sure that it's an invariant.
So that this is
preserved for every firing operation.
This idea here, which first of all originally
ensures that the complement places are occupied, we
will then guarantee that and maintain it
throughout the lifetime of the Petri net.
And that's why we
can then always make
sure that there are actually never
more than k(s) tokens on the place.
Because, so to speak, we will only allow more
tokens to be put on the place if there
are still a corresponding number of
reserve tokens in the complement place.
How can
we achieve this?
We have to make sure that
when firing transitions, this invariant is preserved.
That is, we probably need to
introduce more weights into the Petri net.
Just now
we added places.
If we just added those, they
would be isolated nodes in the
Petri net and there would
be no input or output arrows.
Then, of course, they wouldn't affect
the behavior of the Petri net.
So we still need to
attach them to the Petri net.
How do
we do that?
That always depends on what a
particular transition does to a particular place.
So let's look at
a transition and a place.
Here we describe
how to do that
for a combination of
a transition and a place.
And of course we do that
for every transition and every place,
for all combinations
of transition and place.
When we focus on a transition
and a place, we can ask:
What is this transition
doing with this place?
Does it take
tokens from it?
Does it deposit
tokens in it?
Or is it neutral, so to
speak, with respect to this place?
It could be that t and
s have nothing to do with each
other, that firing t can simply never
change the number of tokens in place s.
How can
this be determined?
Ultimately, you have to
look at this difference.
So one looks at what the
post-weight function of transition t says
for place s and what the pre-weight
function of transition t says for place s.
That expresses how many tokens the transition
t would put in the place s.
And that expresses how many tokens transition
t would take out of place s.
And since there's actually allowed to be
both a forward and a backward arrow,
so to speak, for a transition and a
place, those could also both be positive values.
We're looking at the net behavior,
so to speak, the difference of that.
That's where a
number comes out.
It could be negative, it could
be zero, it could be positive.
If it's negative,
then it means that
the transition is taking tokens
out of the place overall.
This could be, for example, if the post
weight is zero and the pre weight is three.
Then it means that the transition takes three
tokens from the place and gives none to it.
So in total it
takes out three tokens.
It could also be that it
takes four tokens and puts two away.
Then it would take a
net total of two tokens.
So whenever this difference for the certain
t and the certain s is negative,
we add an edge of t to
the complement of s, with weight -n.
Why?
This is a
negative number here.
We negate
that one.
And the corresponding positive
number that comes out,
we write it as a weight to an
edge from the transition t to the complement place.
Because the
idea should be:
Transition t somehow takes a certain
number of tokens from the place s,
maybe two; then these two tokens
should not disappear, but they should
be deposited in
the complement place.
They fill up the
reservoir, so to speak,
from which later firing operations are likely
to place tokens on place s again.
For example transition t, but
in particular also other transitions,
which might want to
deposit something in s.
They should and will
be able to do this
only if there are enough
tokens in the complement place s-bar.
And the same number
of tokens must also
be deposited in s-bar when
tokens are removed from s.
That is, if the transition t
removes tokens from the place s altogether.
What about
the reverse case?
That is, when the transition t
net puts something into the place s.
That is, if the post-weight function for t
with respect to s is greater than the pre-weight
function of t with respect to s,
that is, if this difference is exactly positive.
Then transition t would like to put a
certain number n of tokens into place s.
We may only allow this if
there are not yet so many
tokens there that this addition
of tokens exceeds the allowed capacity.
How can
we guarantee this?
By ensuring that there
is a pre-weight edge from
s-bar to t with exactly
this number n as weight.
Then t should only fire if it
finds a corresponding number of tokens in s-bar.
And this will be the case
exactly (because of this invariant here),
if indeed the sum then
is not greater than k(s).
The sum of the tokens currently
lying in s plus this number n.
These three steps,
these three ideas/applications ensure
that the
desired behavior occurs.
If you look even more closely here,
you can see that it seems a
bit strange that the case "equal
to zero" is not considered at all.
It only says what we
do when this difference is
negative, and what we do
when this difference is positive.
What do we do
if the difference is zero?
Then we
don't do anything.
Why
not?
That would be a combination of
transition t and place s, so
that t takes as many tokens out
of s as it puts in there.
This could either mean that t has
nothing to do with s at all.
So if these two values are both
zero, then there is no reason to
somehow introduce
additional conditions.
Because then t has nothing
to do with s at all.
Or it could mean
that there is indeed
such a loop, where t both takes
tokens from s and puts them there.
And even with
the same value.
But then nothing changes in
the balance, so to speak.
It doesn't change whether
the capacity is kept.
If t takes two tokens
from s and deposits two tokens
there, then this cannot lead
to the capacity bound being exceeded.
This is because t then
does nothing to s on net.
Then we do not need to introduce another
condition or another edge into the Petri net.
Therefore, one does not need
to consider the case additionally.
One only has to deal with
these cases, which are covered here.
What is
achieved by this?
What I had motivated as an idea
then remains as a guarantee, so to speak.
So not only for the start marking m0, but
according to the construction from the previous slide, it
holds for every reachable marking that
m(s) plus m(s-bar) is exactly k(s).
This is exactly what we want
to achieve; and achieve with the construction.
That's the invariant, the
idea that was here.
And the fact that we
insert additional edges between transitions and
complement places ensures that a transition
t is fireable only if the capacities
in its postcondition places
are not yet exhausted.
Because we only allow t to be
fired if there are ultimately enough remaining capacities.
And this is checked/query/guaranteed
by the complement places.
Especially in the case where t puts something
into a place, this is only allowed if a
corresponding number of tokens can
be taken from the complement place.
If not, then t would
not be able to fire.
And this is not because of any
change in the semantics of Petri nets,
but simply because of
these added transition dependencies.
Transitions are
not added.
Places are added, but also
new conditions on the transitions.
We do not prove
now that this works.
You can take my word for it
or try it out on many examples.
You can also think about
why this works in general.
The fact
is, it works.
Let's do this
with an example.
In practice, of course, you
are supposed to do this yourself.
So let's take a look at
the Petri net we had here.
Namely, that was
the Petri net.
If we just look
at the black part.
There was not yet the red
part in this Petri net, and here
there was a 2 on it and here there
was a 1 on it, as these additional annotations.
They must not exist
in a normal Petri net.
So they have
disappeared here now.
But instead, the complement places were
introduced on the one hand, and
additional arrows on
the other hand.
And how is
it done here?
There is the complement place to
s1, and it contains a token.
Why?
Because s1 should contain two tokens, but
in the initial marking it contains only one.
So this "reserve token" is
put in the complement place.
In s2, on the other
hand, there is one token in
the initial marking, and there may
only ever be one token there.
Therefore, there are no reserve
tokens in the complement place.
This explains why s1-bar and s2-bar
look exactly the same and carry
tokens accordingly (or s2-bar just
does not carry any tokens).
And what
about the transitions?
We look at every
combination of s and t.
So, for example,
s1 and t1.
The s1 loses a
net token to t1.
This is because t1 takes exactly one
token from s1 and puts nothing there.
Therefore, according to the construction from here, t1 must
deposit a token in the complement place to s1.
Because t1 takes a token from here from
s1, t1 must deposit a token in s1-bar.
That is why
there is this arrow.
That doesn't mean that t1 doesn't
continue to deposit a token in s2.
So this existing black
output that leaves t1 remains.
It simply
adds an output.
Namely, when t1 takes a token from
s1, it deposits a token in s1-bar.
Then, after this firing, this would
mean (if it were possible, because there
would still be space here; which is not
the case at the moment) that then a token
would move from s1 to s2, but
also a token would be put in s1-bar.
And this is now explained in the
same way for each of these arrows.
Now let's look
at t1 and s2.
There we see that t1 net
puts a token in s2, because
t1 doesn't take anything out
of s2, but puts something there.
So t1 adds a
net token to s2.
Therefore, t1 must take
a token from s2-bar.
This justifies and
forces this arrow here.
For t2 and s1, as well
as s2, it is quite analogous.
So t2 places a token in s1,
therefore must take a token from s1-bar.
And t2 takes
a token from s2,
therefore must put a token
in s2-bar (that's this arrow).
Then we still
have t3 to consider.
The t3 and s1 have
nothing to do with each other.
There is neither an input nor
an output arrow between t3 and s1.
Therefore, there is no connection between
t3 and the complement of s1.
This is exactly a possible
case, which corresponds here to the
case that n = 0 and
would be just neither negative nor positive.
This explains why there is
no connection between t3 and s1-bar.
However, t3 and
s2 are relevant.
Because t3 takes a token from s2,
it must therefore deposit a token in s2-bar.
Between the two places and
three transitions there are six combinations.
The s1-t3 combination
leads to no additional
connection, the other five each lead to an
arrow (exactly the five red arrows we see).
And what
have we achieved?
I already briefly flashed
the reachability graph just now.
Here it is
in its entirety.
First, we see that it looks exactly
the same (except now, of course, for the
indication of the complement places; apart
from that) as the reachability graph we
saw here, which, however, depended on
our looking at this particular semantics.
Where we take extra care, for example, if
we want to fire t1 from this marking,
that we leave that alone if it would
make the number of tokens in s2 too large.
That's exactly what we don't
have to consider explicitly here somehow.
But if we consider the quite
normal semantics of firing Petri nets, it
is also automatically ensured here in the
starting marking (which is that by adding
these two complement
places and their respective
entries) that in this
marking t1 is not fireable.
For what would have to be
for t1 to be allowed to fire?
It would have to be able
to take a token from s1.
Of course it can, because
there is a token there.
But it would also have to be
able to take a token from s2-bar.
And that is exactly
what it cannot do.
Because s2-bar is this position here,
and there is no token there.
That means, there
is no more reserve
which would somehow allow
to put something on s2.
So here, t1 would be effectively
prevented from firing in this marking.
Simply by, in
that case, this connection.
In the same way, the
other connections each allow firing.
So, for example, t2 may
be fired in this start marking.
Also, looking at the same example with
the other semantics, t2 was allowed here
because it didn't somehow violate the
capacitance on any of the places.
And that is automatically given
here, because t2 can fire.
The t2 would like to
put a token in s1.
It checks whether there is any
potential for this, i.e. it checks
whether there is
a token in s1-bar.
This is
the case here.
There is still a token
here precisely because the total
capacity allowed for s1 was
not exhausted with this 1.
This is represented
by this 1.
And therefore the firing of t2
is possible and leads to the
fact that afterwards two tokens lie on
s1 and no token anymore on s1-bar.
So another placing of a token
in s1 would not be allowed.
This would be prevented here (that
one puts further tokens on s1), because
on s1-bar no more
reserve tokens lie at all.
If we now
simply construct the reachability
graph normally for this example shown here
on the left, this graph comes out.
And except for this information for
the complement places, it is equivalent to
the desired reachability graph, which
resulted with the specially built semantics.
So we have achieved our goal, even
without a new kind of Petri net.
Simply by clever use
of the complement places.
You can see this as
a trick, as a modeling
pattern, or as
a systematic construction
that generates a matching Petri net without
capacities for every Petri net with capacities.